Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup III: Veterans' Affairs, undated, 1917-1985 (bulk 1940-1978); 180 linear feet.
  - Series A: Armed Forces and Veterans' Services, undated, 1937-1978 (bulk 1945-1970); 45 linear feet.
    This series has been arranged into the following subseries: Committees (1960-1977), Field Operations (undated, 1948-1956), Geographic Files (1960-1973), J. Greenhut Files (undated, 1943-1956), Jewish War Veterans (1940-1962), Overseas (1944-1966), Regions (1960-1964), Subject Files (undated, 1941-1978), USO Geographic Files (1938, 1958, 1963-1975; bulk 1964-1975), USO Narrative Files (1958-1963), USO Subject Files (undated, 1937, 1941-1975), War Claims (1942-1965), and World War II Subject Files (undated, 1940-1945). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    In 1940, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt requested that JWB, along with the YMCA, YWCA, National Travelers Aid Association, Salvation Army, and the National Catholic Community Service, handle the recreational needs of members of the Armed Forces. As a result, the United Services Organizations (USO) was founded in 1941,36 with JWB participating actively in all aspects of the USO's operations. In addition to its USO activities, the Armed Forces & Veterans' Services (AFVS) division (originally organized in 1917 as the Army and Navy Committee and renamed the Army and Navy Services Division in 1924 before being renamed again in 1947) consisted of two main programs: Field Operations, responsible for determining assignments and managing personnel matters for field staff, and the Overseas Program37, responsible for meeting the religious and related welfare needs of servicemen abroad. This series provides a look at JWB's various activities in support of soldiers and veterans from World War II onward.
    Much of the material collected here-Geographic Files, Overseas, Regions, USO Geographic Files, and USO Narrative Reports-has to do with activities undertaken by JWB and the USO both overseas and at stateside military bases. (In addition to sponsoring and maintaining its own field offices, which covered military installations and neighboring communities, JWB staff also maintained and directed field offices and clubs on behalf of the USO.38) Material on Armed Services Committees throughout the country can be found in the Geographic files, while the Regions files consist largely of administrative and financial matters. The USO Geographic and Narrative reports files provide information about events at USO clubs.
    Also included are the files of Joseph Greenhut, director of Field Operations from 1955 to 1956. Items of note found here include USO-JWB work plans, which give insights into the interactions of the two organizations, and a manual entitled "Publicizing JWB's Armed Services Program: A Manual for USO-JWB Workers and Jewish Chaplains." Other interesting materials can be found in the Committees files, which include meeting minutes for the AFVS Executive Committee, the National Advisory Council on Service to Military and Veterans, and the Cuban Crisis Committee. Additional meeting materials are located in the USO Subject files, which also contain files on USO Presidents Chester Barnard, Lindsey Kimball, Harper Sidley and Executive Director Edwin Bond. (A USO insignia is included in the Army and Navy Subject File.) In addition, the series contains War Claims files, pertaining to JWB's successful claims against the governments of Italy, the Philippines, Austria, Germany, Czechoslovakia and Japan, for compensation for supplies lost, damaged, and destroyed during World War II. (This material includes lists of Jewish Chaplains who served in the European Theatre of Operations during World War II, as well as those in the Pacific Combat Zone and in China, Burma, and India.) Finally, a small amount of material on the Bureau of War Records can be found in the Jewish War Veterans files, and a variety of interesting information can be found in the World War II Subject Files, which consist primarily of news clippings. Topics include refugees, Passover, and the activities of Chaplains. (Several articles focus on the chaplains' efforts to liberate and assist displaced persons and concentration camp survivors.) Clippings pertaining to Joe Rosenthal, who took a famous photograph of the U.S. flag being raised on Iwo Jima, are included here. Also of note are some building plans for a community center in Balboa, which can be found in the Oversized Materials Subgroup.
    36 USO (United Service Organizations) Historical Timeline, www.uso.org/whoweare/ourproudhistory/historicaltimeline/, January 20, 2004
    37 JWB Today: A Guide and a Directory. Part I: Services, Facilities, Staff. Army and Navy Division, pp. 18-21, New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1947
    38 JWB Year Book, volumes 4 to 7 1954-1957, Part 2: The Armed Services Field, New York, National Jewish Welfare Board, 1958
    Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governing Body/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 4: Holiday Files; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series D: Personnel Recruitment and Training/Personnel Services/USO Employee Cards; Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials; Subgroup VI: Oversized Materials. Also I-180: National Jewish Welfare Board Army-Navy Division and I-52: National Jewish Welfare Board Bureau of War Records.
    Restrictions: Field Operations: staff evaluations; Jewish War Veterans (fragile folder of 1947 tribute dinner material; congressional records); USO Geographic-Panama: Chaplaincy; Greenwood, Anne; Reiss, Jacques
    Note: JWB Miscellaneous Boxes 13 and 14 and one unnumbered box are located at end of entire collection. The material relates to Overseas, Regions, Subject Files, War Claims and World War II Subject files.
  - Series B: Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy, undated, 1917-1985 (bulk 1940-1965); 118 linear feet.
    This series has been arranged as follows: Chaplains Files (1918-1985; bulk 1940-1965), General (undated, 1943-1984; bulk 1966-1975), Lay Leaders (1969-1985), Military Installations (1948-1984), Organizations (undated, 1932-1984), Passover (undated, 1930-1973; bulk 1967-1972), Prayer Books and Publications (undated, 1917-1977), Resource Files (undated, 1938-1973), Staff and Past Members (1942-1982; bulk 1960-1974), and Subject Files (undated, 1935-1980). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    The Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy (CJC), founded in 1917 as the Chaplain's Committee of the Jewish Welfare Board, was composed of leaders of the Rabbinical Assembly of America, the Rabbinical Council of America, and the Central Conference of American Rabbis.39 By 1922 the organization had become known as the Sub-Committee on Chaplains and Religious Observance; the name subsequently changed to the Committee on Religious Activities (1940), the Committee on Army and Navy Religious Activities (1942), and the Division of Religious Activities (1947). The Division was renamed the Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy in 1952 and kept this name until 1987, when it became known as the [JWB] Jewish Chaplains' Council. Under any name, the organization's purpose was to recruit and train chaplains and lay leaders to provide services to Jewish military personnel and their families. This subseries documents CJC's activities, with particular focus on World War II and beyond.
    Over half the material found here comprises files on individual chaplains. These files consist mainly of application forms and photographs, as well as narrative reports and correspondence with CJC headquarters, and correspondence with soldiers and their families. This material provides an interesting look at the various activities undertaken by the chaplains during the Second World War, the Korean War, and the Vietnam War, as well as during times of peace. (Also included is a small amount of information on Jacob Frankel, a Jewish chaplain in the Civil War, and the files on Nathan Blechman and Elkan Voorsanger include documents pertaining to their activities during World War I.) Materials of note include the documents concerning David Goldberg, the first Jewish chaplain in the Navy;40 this file includes information on the navy chaplaincy insignia.
    Also of interest is the file on Alexander Goode, posthumous recipient of the Distinguished Service Cross. Goode was one of the Four Chaplains who went down with the SS Dorchester on February 3, 1943. Further material on the Four Chaplains can be found in the General Files and in the Subject Files (in the Rabbis/Chaplains file.) The series contains sizable amounts of material on Aryeh Lev who served as director of CJC from 1945 to 1976 and Joseph Messing, director from 1982 to 1983. Large files also exist on several individuals, including: Benjamin Tintner (this material ranges from the 1920s to the 1950s and covers activities at West Point); Albert Lewin, whose file includes a chaplain's insignia pin; Oscar Lifshutz, the first Jewish Chaplain on combat duty in Korea and recipient of the Bronze Star and several other honors41; Judah Nadich (the first advisor to General Eisenhower on Jewish affairs in the European theater of operations42); and Henry Tavel, the first Jewish chaplain to receive the rank of Colonel in the U.S. Army.43 Also included is a file on Roland Gittelsohn, the first Jewish Chaplain appointed by the Marine Corps, who gave a famous memorial address at Iwo Jima. Material on chaplains' work with displaced people during and after WWII can be found in the files for Mayer Abramowitz, Max Braude, David Max Eichhorn, Herbert S. Eskin, Morris Frank, Herbert Friedman, Meyer J. Goldman, Joseph Miller, Harold Saperstein and Max Wall, among others. (Further material on this can be found in Subgroup III: Veterans' Affairs/Series A: Armed Forces and Veterans' Services/World War II Subject Files.) The series also includes a short run of incomplete chaplaincy applications.
    The lay leaders files include applications, dating between 1969 and 1985, of individuals who supplemented the work of the chaplains and provided religious coverage in areas without chaplains.44 As with the Chaplains' files, these include small photographs which were submitted with the applications.
    The staff and past members files provide information on staff members Joel Balsam (director of CJC, 1977-1978), David Max Eichhorn (director of CJC Field Operations, 1945-1968), Gilbert Kollin (director of CJC, 1979-1981) and A. Elihu Michelson (associate director of CJC, 1952-1975), while the Resource files include orientation materials for new personnel. Also of note are the prayer books, ranging from 1917 to 1956, the Journal of a U.S. Solder (in General Files) and, in Organizations: Military Organizations, the Veterans Administration material regarding a plan to eliminate the chaplains service, and the Military Installations files, which document activities at military bases both in the U.S. and overseas. The Organizations: Jewish Organizations Files provide background on the CJC's relationship with national Jewish agencies, while the Organizations: Military Organizations Files include information on CJC's interactions with the Army, Navy, and Air Force and include the blueprints for a Navy pennant and a 7-light candelabrum. (These are located in the Oversized Materials subgroup.)
    Materials of note in the Subject files include (in Chaplaincy Statistics), lists of WWI chaplains and orthodox chaplains who served on extended active duty between 1861 and 1962, the booklet Brothers in Arms (in the Rabbis/Chaplains file), and the JWB-published book Responsa in Wartime (in the Committee Responsa in Wartime file.) Also included is material on the history of the Chaplaincy (in the History Project and Research Project files.) The War Records file includes material on the participation of Jews in the U.S. armed forces.
    The series also includes a variety of photographs, located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup. These include a 1963 photograph of Chaplain Seymour Brickman with President John F. Kennedy and General Westmoreland and, also from 1963, a photograph of Former President Dwight D. Eisenhower with Chaplain Judah Nadich. A photograph of President Eisenhower with Chaplain Joshua Goldberg and other chaplains can also be found here.
    39 JWB Jewish Chaplains Council/Chaplines on the Web, www.jcca.org/jwb/pastissues/winter99/frame2.html, January 20, 2004
    40 Who's Who in American Jewry, vol. 3, 1938-1939, John Simons, ed. New York: National News Association, Inc., 1938. p. 340
    41 Who's Who in World Jewry: A Biographical Dictionary of Outstanding Jews, Harry Schneiderman & Itzhak J. Carmin, eds, New York: Who's Who in World Jewry, Inc., in cooperation with Monde Publishers, Inc., 1955 p. 473
    42 Who's Who in American Jewry, 1980 Edition, Incorporating the Directory of American Jewish Institutions, Los Angeles: Standard Who's Who, 1980, p. 351
    43 Who's Who in World Jewry: A Biographical Dictionary of Outstanding Jews, Harry Schneiderman & I. J. Carmin Karpman, eds, New York: Who's Who in World Jewry, Inc., 1965, p. 983
    44 JWB Circle, February 1977. p. 4
    Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governing Body/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 4: Holiday Files; Subgroup III: Veterans' Affairs/Series A: Armed Forces and Veterans' Services/War Claims, Subgroup III: Veterans' Affairs/Series A: Armed Forces and Veterans' Services/World War II Subject Files; Subgroup I: Governance/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 4: History Files; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series F: Administrative and Management Services/Subseries 4: Central Purchasing Services; Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials. Also I-249: National Jewish Welfare Board Military Chaplaincy Records.
    Restrictions: The West Point documents (in Organizations: Military Organizations) are very fragile, as are the "Raishes Daas" book in Subject Files, and the High Holy Days and Sabbath Morning materials, in Publications. In addition, some documents in Chaplains, Chaplains Incomplete Applications, Lay Leaders, Military Installations, Overseas Installations, Organizations: Military Organizations, and Subject Files should be restricted. Boxes are marked accordingly.
    Note: JWB Miscellaneous Box 15 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to Subject files.
  - Series C: Women's Organizations' Services, 1930-1982; (bulk 1945-1982); 19 linear feet.
    This series is divided into two subseries: Women's Organizations' Services and Diane Coran files. Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    The Women's Organizations' Services (WOS) Division was organized in 1942 (as the Women's Organizations' Division) to help maintain the morale of men and women in the Armed Forces, and of patients in Veterans' Administration hospitals. WOS was composed of several national Jewish organizations including Hadassah, the National Bureau of Federated Jewish Women's Organizations, the National Council of Jewish Women, the National Federation of Temple Sisterhoods, the National Women's League of the United Synagogue of America, the United Order True Sisters, and B'nai B'rith. WOS ran four main programs: Serve-a-Camp, which, through local committees, sent supplies to JWB-USO workers stationed at isolated camps and bases; Serve-a-Chaplain, which shipped supplies to chaplains overseas; Serve-an-Overseas Hospitality Center, and Serve-a-Hospital, which provided gifts to patients in veterans hospitals and Army and Navy general hospitals.45 All of these programs offered large quantities of Hanukah, Purim, and Passover items to soldiers and patients in veterans' hospitals.
    This series documents the activities of the various organizations affiliated with WOS; these organizations raised money and collected goods-ranging from kosher food for Passover, to gifts for Chanukah and books for chaplains' libraries-for the chaplains, lay leaders, and Veterans' Administration Voluntary Service volunteers. Also included here are the files of Diana Bernstein Coran, who served as director of WOS beginning in 1957. These files consist of program materials for Chanukah, Passover, Purim, Rosh Hashanah, Yom Kippur, Sukkot, and the Shabbat, and contain recipes, plays, meeting ideas, crafts, games, fund raising ideas, bibliographies and temple services in Hebrew and English. Meeting minutes and news clippings can also be found here, while some photographs are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup. Of particular note are a medal from walk-a-thon, mezuzah parchments, a vinyl record titled "Shabbat Sholom" (to be found in the Audio/Visual Materials subgroup) and a campfire girls poster. Also of note are "A Book of Jewish Thoughts" and "The Oppenheim Pictures."
    45 JWB Today: A Guide and a Directory, Part I: Services Facilities Staff, New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1947, p. 24
    Related Materials: Subgroup III: Veterans Affairs/Series B: Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy/Passover; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series F: Administrative and Management Services/Subseries 4: Central Purchasing Services; Subgroup I: Governing Body/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 4: Holiday Files.
- Subgroup IV: Affiliated Organizations, undated, 1889-1979 (bulk 1930-1975); 75 linear feet.
  This subgroup is divided into four series: Series A: National Affiliated Organizations, Series B: World Confederation of Jewish Community Centers, Series C: World Federation of YM & YWHA and JCC, and Series D: YMHA. Arrangement: Arranged alphabetically.
  The Affiliated Organizations subgroup documents JWB's sponsorship and partnership of other national Jewish organizations, most notably are the YMHA, B'nai B'rith, American Jewish Historical Society, and World Federation of YM & YWHAs and JCCs. This subgroup reflects the difficulties faced by these organizations both during and after both World Wars. Also partly documented is the growth of the Jewish Center movement within the country and Canada. Material related to the affiliated organizations can also be found in the Jewish Community Center subgroup.
  - Series A: National Affiliated Organizations, 1915-1978 (bulk 1938-1950); 6.5 linear feet.
    This series has been arranged into the following categories: Various Organizations, AJHS, National Association of Jewish Center Workers, and NAJCW/Louis Kraft. Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    The series National Affiliated Organizations reflects the relationship between JWB and the various organizations that allied themselves under the umbrella of JWB. With the exception of NAJCW, which came into existence because of the JWB, the other organizations were founded as individual groups to stand on their own merit. After WWI and WWII, however, many organizations had difficulty in obtaining the funds needed for day-to-day operations. These organizations chose to become affiliated with the JWB in order to receive some of the needed funds from JWB itself. JWB actively sought some of these organizations others contacted JWB themselves. "A Century of the Jewish Community Center Movement" states that:
    "The National Association of Jewish Center Workers, founded in 1918... conducts annual conferences, publishes papers, stimulates research in various aspects of Center work and issues a quarterly magazine devoted to the professional interests of its membership."46
    The records document the correspondence between JWB and the assorted organizations concerning the representation and membership issues involved with joining the larger organization. B'nai B'rith's material is a good example as to how the organizations functioned after joining JWB and the concerns that arose around the affiliation. Also highlighted is the relationship between JWB and its professional staff who belonged to NAJCW.
    Of special interest are the materials relating to Jewish History Week, which was sponsored by the American Jewish Historical Society to promote the rich history of the Jews in America.
    Types of documents include reports, lists, correspondence, budgets, memoranda, minutes, annual meeting programs, speeches, by-laws, photographs (located in Audio/Visual Subgroup), newspaper clippings, donation information, building plans (some are located in Oversized Materials Subgroup), radio play transcripts, promotional material, "NAJCW Newsletter", resolutions, personnel codes, committee findings, and a honor roll of Jewish Center Workers who served in the Armed Forces during WWII.
    46 Kraft, Louis. A Century of the Jewish Community Center Movement. New York: Astoria Press, 1953
  - Series B: World Confederation of Jewish Community Centers (WCJCC), 1974-1979; 1 linear foot.
    The WCJCC was founded in May 1977 in Jerusalem to succeed the World Federation of YM & YWHA and JCCs. The founding organizations include the JWB, Community Center Bureau of the Fonds Social Juif Unifie, European Association of Jewish Community Service, Argentine Federation of Maccabi Community Centers, Association for Jewish Youth of Great Britain, and Israel Federation of Community Centers. As indicated by their website, the objectives of the WCJCC are:
    1. To encourage the development of Jewish Community Centers and enable them to enhance Jewish continuity, strengthen Jewish identification, further Jewish and Israel cultures and deepen Jewish knowledge and values in Jewish communities throughout the world.
    2. To express and enrich the sense of unity between the Jewish people around the world and the people and State of Israel and to help build understanding and relationships among the Jewish people in the various lands.
    3. To serve as a symbol of the common purposes shared by all Jewish Community Centers.
    4. To serve as a council of national and continental federations of Jewish Community Centers and other interested bodies, committed to the work of Jewish Community Centers throughout the world.
    5. To provide a forum and vehicle for exchange of information and to expedite communication among Jewish Community Centers in various lands.
    6. To seek ways to aid directly the development and enrichment of Jewish Community Centers in Jewish communities not represented by a national or continental federation.47
    The series consists of Morton Mandel and Herbert Millman's correspondence and subject files as Director and Executive Director of WCJCC. Of particular interest are the documents relating to WCJCC's conferences.
    Types of documents include correspondence, memoranda, by-laws, and reports.
    47 The World Confederation of Jewish Community Centers (WCJCC) - About Us, http://www.wcjcc.org/AboutUs.aspx
  - Series C: World Federation of YM & YWHAs and JCCs, 1927-1975 (bulk 1940-1970); 46.5 linear feet.
    The series has been arranged into the following subseries: Alphabetical Files (1927-1966), Emanuel Berlatsky (1970-1973), Countries Overseas (1949-1960), Foreign Countries (1936-1966), Geographic Files (1946-1967), Jerusalem Y Building Fund (1948-1971), Jerusalem Y Maintenance Files (1948-1976, bulk 1950-1970), Jerusalem Y Contribution Correspondence (1952-1967), Jerusalem Y Subject Files (1949-1967, bulk 1955-1963), Meetings and Biennials (1952, 1956-1970, bulk 1949-1959), Bernard Resnikoff (1948-1974, bulk 1967-1970), Subject Files (1947-1973), and Asher Tarmon (1946-1975). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    The World Federation of YM & YWHA and JCCs was founded on January 1, 1947 by the JWB, National Council of YM & YWHA's of Canada, National YMHA's of Australia, and the Association for Jewish Youth of England. The Articles of Federation from 1961 state the objectives as: